On the River Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
On the River Collection
1986 - 1993
Producers Edward P. Swyer and Ernest A. Arico
NPkMC-222-082
152 3/4 inch master tapes, 300 1/2 tapes and 300 DVD's (2 1/2 inch tapes and 2 DVD's of each episode are available for use)
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
"On the River" was a documentary TV series concerning the Hudson River and its surroundings. It was developed to inform people about the River as an economical and a recreational resource.
Related Collections
Alexander Saunders Papers: Records Relating to the Storm King Case, 1962 - 1966
Cornwall Pumped Storage Pumped Storage Collection, 1953 - 1981
Grim Collection: Hudson River Fisheries Investigation, 1965 - 1968
Hudson River Conservation Society, Inc. Collection, 1963 - 2005
Hudson River Environmental Society Collection, 1963 - 2005
Hudson River Valley Commission Collection: Records Relating to the Storm King Case, 1966 – 1967
Hudson River Valley Greenway Council Collection, 1989 - 1996
Hudson Valley GREEN Collection, 1981 - 2002
Scenic Hudson, Inc. Administrative History Collection, 1960 - 2000
Scenic Hudson Collection: Records relating to the Storm King Case, 1963 - 1981
Scenic Hudson Decision Hearings Transcripts Collection, 1977 - 1980
Senator Mrs. Whitney N. Seymour Jr. Papers: Records Relating to the Storm King Case, 1962 - 1978
Collection Overview
The "On the River" collection consists of 153 videotapes, documenting the impact of the Hudson River on the area and how it has been a recreational and economic resource to those on its shore or in the surrounding areas. It tells stories up and down the river about well-known places and near-hidden treasures. The videos provide snapshots of the River activities and subjects, chronicling many topics, including the return of the Bald Eagles to the Hudson, ice yachting and the history of whaling on the Hudson River. The videos also include historic sites, such as Wilderstein Estate, and West Point. People profiles include author Robert Boyle, marine artist Anton Otto Fischer, and Lowell Thomas.
Acquisitions Information
Edward P. Swyer presented the videotapes and provided funding to preserve the collection to the Marist College Library in 1998. Ernest A. Arico presented additional videotapes to the Marist College Library in 2004.
Historical Note
The "On the River" documentary was originally aired on WTSA-channel 62, a Kingston, N.Y. - based station. It was hosted by WTZA news anchor Brian Madden and aired Sunday evenings from 1986 to 1993. Edward P. Swyer produced all the episodes up to 1991. Ernest A. Arico produced twenty episodes in the final two years.
The series is an extensive recording of activities and enterprises demonstrating how the Hudson River has been an abundant resource for people who live along or near it. The show’s focus on the Hudson as a recreational and economic resource, as well as its impact on those who live and work along its shores.
In October of 1998, the Swyer produced collection was given to Marist College to serve as an educational tool not only for the students, but also for the people in the Hudson Valley who want to learn more about the River. The hope of this collection was that future generations would commit themselves to the preservation of this historic and beautiful waterway.
At the time Swyer donated the collection, the Marist College Library Archives and Special Collections received a grant from Swyer to preserve and support the collection. The funds were used to process the “On the River” Collection as well as publicize the collection to students, faculty, and the public.
In 2004, the twenty additional episodes produced by Ernest A. Arico were donated to Marist College. These episodes were well received and won various awards including two New York State Emmys for his work on the History of Blacks in the Hudson Valley and the his two part series on the life of John Burroughs. Arico also was awarded with two New York State Broadcasters Awards during his time as producer.
Restrictions to Access
There are no restrictions on this collection
Physical Access Restriction
Access to materials in the collection require use of a videotape player or a DVD player.
Collection is arranged intoseven series: 1. Episodes airing in 1986, 2. Episodes airing in 1987, 3. Episodes airing in 1988, 4. Episodes airing in 1989, 5. Episodes airing in 1990, 6. Episodes airing in 1991 - 1993, and 7. Extra clip videos, archives, and work tapes.
Materials in series are arranged chronologically.
- 1. Episodes airing in 1986, Box: 1 (Episode 1)
  Videorecordings of episodes airing in 1986.
  Chronological
  - Voyage on the Clearwater: Riverkeeper Concept(First Copy) (Episode 1.1, Box 1)
  - Voyage on the Clearwater: Riverkeeper Concept (second copy, no DVD) (Episode 1.2, Box 1)
  - Fishermen, barge repairs, tourism, lighthouses(Hudson River Task Force) (Episode 2, Box 1)
  - Dutchess County tourism, Maritime Center, and Scenic Hudson (Episode 3, Box 1)
  - Artist Elizabeth Mowry, Sailing (Episode 4, Box 1)
  - Warren McKeon, Rondout Bell, Pirate Canoe Club (Episode 5, Box 1)
  - A River Spirit (Episode 6, Box 1)
  - William O'Benson yacht, Open Space Institute, Artist Don Nice, M.V. Commander (Episode 7, Box 1)
  - Part I: Port of Albany - Ralph Manna (Episode 8.1, Box 1)
  - Part III: Port of Albany - Ralph Manna (Episode 8.2, Box 1)
  - (Segment from show) The Navigator (Episode 9.1, Box 1)
  - (Full Episode) The Navigator, Esopus Beach (Episode 9.2, Box 1)
  - Hudson River Museum, Hudson Valley Winery, and the Hudson River Environmental Society (Episode 10, Box 1)
  - The DEC, Photographer Laura Feldman (Episode 11, Box 1)
  - Hinchey&Ingalsbe Debate (Episode 12, Box 1)
  - (segment, no DVD) Steamship Society - Roger Mabie (Episode 13.1, Box 1)
  - (Full Episode) Steamship Society, Grumman Goose (Episode 13.2, Box 1)
  - Duck Hunters, Museum of the Hudson Hughlands (Episode 14, Box 1)
  - Wilderstein Mansion (Episode 15, Box 1)
  - Peter Dwyer, Certified Marine Services (Episode 16, Box 1)
  - Black Bear Trading Post, Clean Water Act (Episode 17, Box 1)
  - Photography by Ted Spiegel, the Poughkeepsie Railroad Bridge (Episode 18, Box 1)
  - David Crawford Mansion (Episode 19, Box 1)
- 2. Episodes airing in 1987, Boxes: 1 - 3 (Episode 2)
  Videorecordings of episodes airing in 1987.
  - Ice Buoys (Episode 21, Box 1)
  - "How to Build a Boat" (Episode 22, Box 1)
  - The Eleanor Tug Boat, Bait Shop (Episode 23, Box 1)
  - Clearwater Winter Maintenance, IBM Photo Display (Episode 24, Box 1)
  - (original airing) Trailside Museum (Episode 25.1, Box 1)
  - (second copy) Trailside Museum (Episode 25.2, Box 1)
  - (original airing) Sewage Treatment, Photographer Ernest Warnacke (Episode 26.1, Box 2)
  - (second copy 3/4 in. tape only) Sewage Treatment, Photographer Ernest Warnacke (Episode 26.2, Box 2)
  - Ice Fishing, Old Photos, Mansions (Episode 27, Box 2)
  - Hudson Valley Boat Show (Episode 28, Box 2)
  - World Fishing and Outdoor Expo, Ice Yachting (Episode 29, Box 2)
  - (original airing 3/4 in. tape only) Fly Fishing (jumpy tape, second copy better to see) (Episode 30.1, Box 2)
  - (second copy) Fly Fishing (Episode 30.2, Box 2)
  - Bald Eagles, The "Innocent Eye" Exhibit (Episode 31, Box 2)
  - John Sanders and the PCB's in the River (Episode 32, Box 2)
  - Cleaning PCB's off Fish (Episode 33, Box 2)
  - John Cronin (Representative) Hudson River Fishermen's Association Lawsuit (Episode 34, Box 2)
  - Stanley Graham - Hudson River Valley Video (Episode 35, Box 2)
  - Shad Fishing (Episode 36, Box 2)
  - Boat Safety and Regulations - U.S. Power Squadron Ralph Smith Jr. (Episode 37, Box 2)
  - Clearwater-Educational Sail (Episode 38, Box 2)
  - Woody Guthrie with Pete Seger (Episode 39, Box 2)
  - Dr. John Johnsen - Geologist (Episode 40, Box 2)
  - Andy Kahnle - DEC, Laura Keyes (Episode 41, Box 2)
  - Patrol Boats of Dutchess and Ulster County (Episode 42, Box 2)
  - Troy (Episode 43, Box 2)
  - Dr. Andrew Hendricks and the Dutch Influence and the Replica of the Half Moon (Episode 44, Box 2)
  - Steve Nack and Bass Spawning, NYC Environmental Conference (Episode 45, Box 2)
  - Regatta, Skigakker, Revival of the Waterfront (Episode 46, Box 2)
  - Troy Lock and Dam (Episode 47, Box 2)
  - Water Chestnuts (Episode 48, Box 2)
  - Antique Boat Society, the Driftwood Showboat (Episode 49, Box 2)
  - Coxsackie (Episode 50, Box 2)
  - Hudson River Cruising Guide, Hudson River Symposium (Episode 51, Box 2)
  - Rip Van Winkle Boat - Sightseeing (Episode 52, Box 2)
  - Iona Land Marsh (Episode 53, Box 3)
  - Verplank Fish Hatchery (Episode 54, Box 3)
  - Hudson River Dayliner (Episode 55, Box 3)
  - (original airing) Little Red Lighthouse (Episode 56.1, Box 3)
  - (second copy) Little Red Lighthouse (Episode 56.2, Box 3)
  - (third copy 3/4 in. tape only) Little Red Lighthouse (Episode 56.3, Box 3)
  - Clermont State Historical Site (Episode 57, Box 3)
  - Photo Exhibit - Robert Ketchum, Do It Yourself Boat Building (Episode 58, Box 3)
  - Hudson River Sailboat Race (Episode 60, Box 3)
  - Driftwood, J.P. Cruise Lines (Episode 61, Box 3)
  - Historic Hudson Valley Diner Gala Event in NYC (Episode 62, Box 3)
  - Hudson River Lighthouse (Episode 63, Box 3)
  - Lil' Rip Tugboat (Episode 64, Box 3)
  - Wave Hill (Episode 65, Box 3)
  - Norrie Point Aquarium (Episode 66, Box 3)
  - A Rondout Christmas (Episode 67, Box 3)
  - Railroads (Episode 68, Box 3)
- 3. Episodes airing in 1988, Boxes: 3 - 4 (Episode 3)
  Videorecordings of episodes airing in 1988.
  - Chelsea Proposed Developments (Episode 69, Box 3)
  - Hudson River Greenway Proposition (Episode 70, Box 3)
  - Bowdoin Park (Episode 71, Box 3)
  - Ned Leadbetter's Photo Exhibit (Episode 72, Box 3)
  - Hunting and Fishing Expo in Kingston Armory (Episode 73, Box 3)
  - Beach Combing (Episode 74, Box 3)
  - Water Testing - Sawmill River (Episode 75, Box 3)
  - Lenoir Preserve (Episode 76, Box 3)
  - Ice Breaker - Coast Guard Cutter Raritan (Episode 77, Box 3)
  - Boat Show and Outdoor World Expo (Episode 78, Box 3)
  - Washington Headquarters - State Historic Site (Episode 79, Box 3)
  - Brick Industry (Episode 80, Box 3)
  - Albany Steamboat Festival (Episode 81, Box 3)
  - Preparing for Spring - the Clearwater, Frank Parslow, the Saugerties Coast Guard, and the Ulster Marine (Episode 82, Box 4)
  - The Electic Launch Company (Episode 83, Box 4)
  - Bass Fishing (Episode 84, Box 4)
  - Shad Fishing (Episode 85, Box 4)
  - Bannerman's Island (Episode 86, Box 4)
  - Waterfront Planning (Episode 87, Box 4)
  - Poughkeepsie Regatta, Kingston Shad Festival (Episode 88, Box 4)
  - (original airing) "Funny Fish" (Episode 89.1, Box 4)
  - (second copy 3/4 in. tape only) "Funny Fish" (Episode 89.2, Box 4)
  - 79th Street Boat Basin (Episode 90, Box 4)
  - (original airing) Constitution Island Marsh Canoe Trip (Episode 91.1, Box 4)
  - (second copy 3/4 in. tape only) Constitution Island Marsh Canoe Trip (Episode 91.2, Box 4)
  - Trolley Museum, Steam Voices (Episode 92, Box 4)
  - Sea Planes, Gondolas (Episode 93, Box 4)
  - The Red Hot Mamas (Episode 94, Box 4)
  - Painter John Gould, Pilot's Club Dinner (Episode 95, Box 4)
  - Peregrine Falcon (Episode 96, Box 4)
  - On the River's Second Anniversary (Episode 97, Box 4)
  - Highland Falls Marina, My Derse House (Episode 98, Box 4)
  - the Sequoia (Episode 99, Box 4)
  - Exhibit - Hudson River Ship Models (Episode 100, Box 4)
  - The Nature Conservancy and Marshes (Episode 101, Box 4)
  - Marlborough's Bicentennial (Episode 102, Box 4)
  - "The Rattlesnake," Caviar (Episode 103, Box 4)
  - Scenic Hudson's 25th Anniversary (Episode 104, Box 4)
  - Bass Tournament (Episode 105, Box 4)
- 4. Episodes airing in 1989, Boxes: 4 - 5 (Episode 4)
  Videorecordings of episodes airing in 1989.
  - River Estates - Mills Mansion, Vanderbilt Mansion, and the Morse Home (Episode 106, Box 4)
  - (original airing) Religious Estates - Marist Brothers Monastery, The Cabrine Center, and Mt. Saint Alphonsus (Episode 107.1, Box 4)
  - (second copy) Religious Estates - Marist Brothers Monastery, The Cabrine Center, and Mt. Saint Alphonsus (Episode 107.2, Box 4)
  - Indian Point 2 Nuclear Power Plant (Episode 108, Box 5)
  - Mid-Hudson Boat Show (Episode 109, Box 5)
  - Ice-Breaker - Sturgeon Bay (Episode 110, Box 5)
  - Animal Tracking - Norrie State Park (Episode 112, Box 5)
  - Maple Syruping (Episode 113, Box 5)
  - Spring Rush, Hudson River Environmental Society Symposium (Episode 114, Box 5)
  - White Water Rafting (Episode 115, Box 5)
  - The Intrepid (Episode 116, Box 5)
  - Stockport Flats, Hudson River Club, Half Moon Replica (Episode 117, Box 5)
  - West Point Band - 1812 Overture (Episode 118, Box 5)
  - Bass River Project (Episode 120, Box 5)
  - (original airing) Ferry Captain, Venezuelan Explorer (Episode 121.1, Box 5)
  - (second copy 3/4 in. tape only) Ferry Captin, Venezuelan Explorer (Episode 121.2, Box 5)
  - Peregrine Falcon (Episode 123, Box 5)
  - Ellis Island, Sea History (Episode 124, Box 5)
  - Ashokan Reservoir (Episode 125, Box 5)
  - (segment) Christmas Eve at Olana (Episode 126.1, Box 5)
  - (full episode) Christmas Special at Olana, Handbell Ringers (Episode 126.2, Box 5)
- 5. Episodes airing in 1990, Box: 5 (Episode 5)
  Videorecordings of episodes airing in 1990.
  - West Point Museum (Episode 127, Box 5)
  - D& H Canal Museum (Episode 128, Box 5)
  - Wappinger Creek Bridge Controversy (Episode 129, Box 5)
  - Anton Otto Fischer - Marine Artist (Episode 130, Box 5)
  - Earth Day Special (Episode 132, Box 5)
  - (original airing) Model Boat Builder, Saugerties Lighthouse Restoration (Episode 133.1, Box 5)
  - (second copy 3/4 in. tape only) Model Boat Builder, Saugerties Lighthouse Restoration (Episode 133.2, Box 5)
  - Albany Crew, Harverstarw Marina (Episode 134, Box 5)
- 6. Episodes airing in 1991 - 1993, Boxes: 5 - 6 (Episode 6)
  Videorecordings of episodes airing in 1991 - 1993
  - History of Blacks in the Hudson Valley (Episode 135, Box 5)
  - History of Whaling in the Hudson River (Episode 136, Box 5)
  - Montgomery Place (Episode 137, Box 5)
  - Benson Lossing (Episode 138, Box 6)
  - John Burroughs Part I (Episode 139, Box 6)
  - John Burroughs Part II (Episode 140, Box 6)
  - Olana Mansion (Episode 141, Box 6)
  - Desmond Estate (Episode 142, Box 6)
  - John Jay Homestead (Episode 143, Box 6)
  - Beekman Arms (Episode 144, Box 6)
  - Samuel F.B. Morse and Locust Grove (Episode 145, Box 6)
  - Roland Van Zandt (Episode 146, Box 6)
  - The Life and Times of Mathew Vassar (Episode 147, Box 6)
  - Poughkeepsie Railroad Bridge (Episode 148, Box 6)
  - New York State Military Academy (Episode 149, Box 6)
  - Conversation with Robert F. Kennedy Jr. (Episode 150, Box 6)
  - Lowell Thomas Parts I&II (Episode 151, Box 6)
  - Early History of Central Hudson (Episode 152, Box 6)
  - Zebra Mussels in the Hudson River (Episode 153, Box 6)
- 7. Extra clip videos, archives, and work tapes, Box: 6 (Episode 7)
  Videorecordings of other recordsings
  Subject
  - Freedom Row '89 (Episode Extras 1, Box 6)
  - West Point, Bear Mountain, River Scenes, Birds (Episode Extras 2, Box 6)
  - Various Hudson River Scenes (Episode Extras 3, Box 6)
  - Woodstock '94 Special (Episode Extras 4, Box 6)
  - Extra Clips - Bannerman's Island, the Clearwater, the Commander (no sound) (Episode Archive 24, Box 6)
  - Washington's Headquarters (Episode Archive 27, Box 6)
  - Shots aboard the Clearwater (Episode Archive 38, Box 6)
  - West Point Concert, Poughkeepsie Rural Cemetery (Episode Archive 60, Box 6)
  - Extra Clips (Episode Archive 65, Box 6)
  - Waterfront planning (3/4 inch tape only) (Episode Worktape 87, Box 6)